Guide to the Alice and Rita Lawrencepapers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Alice and Rita Lawrence Papers,
1874-1935.
Lawrence, Alice Montgomery, ca. 1865-1895.
6.5 linear ft. ( 1 document box and 2 flat boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4079011
History
Alice Montgomery Lawrence and Rita (Margarita) Woodhull Lawrence (ca. 1867-1939?) were well-known amateur actresses in New York City during the 1880s and 1890s. Rita Lawrence also wrote an autobiographical memoir, Amateurs & Actors of the 19TH-20TH Centuries (American, English, Itlaian), (Menton, Fr., 1936).
Scope and Content
Correspondence, programs, clippings, and other theatrical memorabilia relating the the careers of Alice and Rita Lawrence.
Subjects
Lawrence, Margarita Woodhull, ca. 1867-1939?; New York (N.Y.)--Social life and customs.; Amateur theater--New York (State)--New York.; Theater--New York (State)--New York.; Performing arts--New York (State)--New York.; Actresses.
Acquisition
1971 M-71 Brander Matthews Dramatic Museum Transfer
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence and Manuscripts
  This series contains incoming and outgoing correspondence to Alice and Rita Lawrence, and is arranged in alphabetical order by name.
  - Allen, Edward Heron "I love you so!" [n.p.], 5 February 1888 1 page a.ms.s. (poem)1 (Box 1)
  - Amory, Rhina [Mrs. William, Jr.] To Rita Lawrence [New York], 12 February 1887 2 page a.l.s.1 (Box 1)
  - Amory, William Jr. To Rita Lawrence [New York], 20 February 1887 2 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Backus, George To Rita Lawrence [New York], 1893 2 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Barber, M. Louise To Alice M. Lawrence Brooklyn, 15 January 1886 4 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Barber, M. Louise To Rita W. Lawrence Brooklyn, 16 January 1886 4 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Barnard, Anna E. To Alice & Rita W. Lawrence [New York], 14 May 1888 1 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Barry, Helen To Rita Lawrence [New York], 1890 2 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Bloom, Edward L. Receipt for Theatre Rental New York, 6 February 1893 1 page a.d.s. (Box 1)
  - Bond, Frederick To Rita Lawrence [New York], 1888 2 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Bond, Frederick To Rita Lawrence [New York], 23 March 1888 3 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Booth, Agnes To Alice M. Lawrence [New York], 6 March 1888 2 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Burroughs, William To Alice M. Lawrence Larchmont, NY, 10 April 1892 3 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Carter, Edward To Rita Lawrence New York, 23 April 1888 2 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Collins, Laura Sedgwick Receipt for Salary [n.p.], 19 May 1892 1 page a.d.s (Box 1)
  - Corlies, Susan M. To Alice M. Lawrence Pelham Manor [NY], 11 November 1888 4 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Coward, Edward Fales To Rita Lawrence [New York], 11 February 1887 1 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Curtis, Henry Holbrook To William Thomas Lawrence [New York], 1890 2 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Cutting, Robert Livingston Jr. To Rita Lawrence [New York], [1890] 3 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - de Blossieres, A. G. To Miss Lawrence [New York], 17 April 1888 1 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - De Forest, Fanny A. To Miss Lawrence [n.p.], 18 February 1893 3 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - De Forest, Harriet To Miss Lawrence Summit, NJ, 18 February 1893 2 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - de Wolfe, Elsie Anderson To Alice M. Lawrence [New York], [23 February 1888] 2 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Dixey, Henry E. To Alice Lawrence [New York], 22 December 1885 1 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Drew, Josephine Baker (Mrs. John) To Alice M. Lawrence [New York], [n.d.] 2 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Eldridge, Louisa To Alice M. Lawrence [New York], 20 February 1889 2 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Fitch, Clyde To Alice M. Lawrence [New York], 9 April 1892 3 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Frohman, Daniel Statement about Alice M. & Rita Lawrence New York, 1890 1 page t.ms. (carbon) (Box 1)
  - Gaunt, Percy Receipt for Orchestra Payment New York, 189- 1 page a.d.s (Box 1)
  - Gwynne, Edith To Alice M. Lawrence [New York], [ca. December 1887] 4 page a.l.s (Box 1)
  - Gwynne, Edith To Alice M. Lawrence [New York], [ca. January 1888] 4 page a.l.s (Box 1)
  - Gwynne, Edith To Alice M. Lawrence [New York], 1 January 1888 1 a.p.c. (Box 1)
  - Henderson, Grace R. To Alice M. Lawrence [New York], 1890 1 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Henderson, Grace R. To Alice M. Lawrence [New York], [1890 ?] 2 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Hoey, Josephine To Alice M. Lawrence [New York], 14 February 1889 2 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Jackson, Sir Harry V. To Alice M. Lawrence London, 8 July 1835 1 page t.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Kelcey, Caroline Hill (Mrs. Herbert) To Alice M. Lawrence [London], [December n.y.] 1 a.n. (Box 1)
  - Kelcey, Herbert To Alice M. Lawrence [New York}, 19 March 1889 2 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Kelcey, Herbert To Alice M. Lawrence [New York], 1890 1 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Kelcey, Herbert To Alice M. Lawrence New York, [4 February 1890] 2 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Laughton, Mrs. McAllister To Alice M. Lawrence Washington, 17 February 1886 1 telegram (Box 1)
  - Laughton, Mrs. McAllister To Sophie Clinch Tilley Lawrence Washington, 18 February 1886 1 telegram (Box 1)
  - Lawrence, Alice Montgomery [to Herbert Kelcey] To Alice M. Lawrence [New York], [1890] 3 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Lawrence, Alice Montgomery Copyright Certificate Washington, 4 March 1891 1 page ms.d. (Box 1)
  - Lawrence, Rita Woodhull Diary [v.p.], 1891-1895 1 volume a.ms.s. (Box 1)
  - Lawrence, William Thomas To Alice M. Lawrence New York, 14 April 1892 1 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Lawrence, William Thomas "Fresh Air Home" Account New York, 15-18 February 1889 2 page a.d. (Box 1)
  - Nicholas, George W. Receipt New York, 20 February 1889 1 page a.d.s. (Box 1)
  - Lawrence, William Thomas Account Book New York, 28 March - 12 April 1892 ? 1 page a.d. (Box 1)
  - Lewis, James To Rita Lawrence New York, 13 April 1892 1 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Lyman, Laura C. To Alice M. Lawrence New York, 9 December 1892 4 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Lyon, B. de (Mrs. John Doane) To Alice M. Lawrence New York, 2 March n.y. 1 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Madison, Mathilde To Alice M. Lawrence [n.p.], [n.d.] 2 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Madison, Mathilde To Alice M. Lawrence New York, 1 November 1886 2 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Madison, Mathilde To Rita Lawrence New York, ca. February 1887 2 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Manierre, Alfred Lee To Rita Lawrence New York, 22 April 1898 3 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Martin, Mary T. To Alice M. Lawrence New York, 23 May n.y. 3 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Meyer, Charles Receipt for Wigs New York, 22 April 1893 1 page a.d.s. (Box 1)
  - Ninton, Telfair Mariott To Rita Lawrence [n.p.], 1890 1 card a.n.s. (Box 1)
  - Murray, Henry Alexander To Alice M. Lawrence New York, 5 January 1886 2 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Pierson, Henrietta B.H. To Sophie Clinch Tilley Lawrence New York, 1 March 1889 2 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Potter, Cora Urquhart (Mrs. James Brown) To Alice M. Lawrence [n.p.], [n.d.] 2 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Potter, Cora Urquhart (Mrs. James Brown) To Alice M. Lawrence New York, ca. 1884 1 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Potter, Cora Urquhart (Mrs. James Brown) To Alice M. Lawrence New York, February 1886 6 page a.l.s. Note: With copies of 3 related letters (Box 1)
  - Potter, Cora Urquhart (Mrs. James Brown) To Alice M. Lawrence [n.p.], 24 May 1886 1 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Potter, Cora Urquhart (Mrs. James Brown) To Alice M. Lawrence [London], 28 July 1886 6 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Pryor, Sara Agnes Rice (Mrs. Roger Atkinson) To Alice M. Lawrence New York, 7 December 1888 3 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Pryor, Sara Agnes Rice (Mrs. Roger Atkinson) To Rita Lawrence New York, 7 December 1888 2 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Reeve, C.C. To Alice M. Lawrence New York, 21 January 1893 1 page t.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Roberts, R.A. To Alice M. Lawrence New York, 1891 1 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Roeder, Benjamin A. To Rita Lawrence New York, 29 March 1890 1 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Roosa, Daniel Bennett St. John To Sophie Clinch Tilley Lawrence New York, 11 December 1892 2 page a.l.s.1 Russell, Robert Howard To Alice M. Lawrence New York, 20 March 1889 2 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Ryan, J.S. To Rita Lawrence New York, 16 November 1890 1 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Shortridge, Laura Virginia To Alice M. Lawrence New York, 1892 2 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Shortridge, Laura Virginia To Alice M. Lawrence New York, 7 December 1892 7 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Suydam, Walter L. To Alice M. Lawrence New York, 2 April 1893 1 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Teall, Florence Rissell (Mrs. Oliver Sumner) and Cora Urquhart Potter (Mrs. James Brown) To Alice M. Lawrence Washington, 18 February 1886 1 page telegram (Box 1)
  - Tosti, Francesco Paolo To Alice M. Lawrence London, 16 December n.y. 4 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Warner, Franklin Mott To Rita Lawrence New York, 1890 1 page a.n. (Box 1)
  - Weekes, Frederic Delano To Rita Lawrence New York, 1888 1 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Wendell, Evert Janson To Alice M. Lawrence New York, 24 February 1891 2 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Wendell, Evert Jansen To Rita Lawrence New York, 3 January 1915 2 page t.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Wheatcroft, Nelson To Alice M. Lawrence [n.p.], [n.d.] 1 page a.n.s. (Box 1)
  - Wheatcroft, Nelson To Rita Lawrence New York, 1890 2 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Wheatcroft, Nelson To Sophie Clinch Tilley Lawrence New York, 26 march 1890 2 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Wheatcroft, Nelson To Sophie Clinch Tilley Lawrence New York, 14 April 1890 2 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Wheatcroft, Nelson To Alice M. Lawrence New York, 21 April 1890 1 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Wheatcroft, Nelson To Rita Lawrence New York, 6 May 1890 1 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Wheatcroft, Nelson To Rita Lawrence New York, 25 June 1890 2 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Wheatcroft, Nelson To Rita Lawrence New York, 9 December 1890 2 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Wheatcroft, Nelson To Alice M. Lawrence New York, 21 February 1891 1 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Wheatcroft, Nelson To Rita Lawrence New York, 17 April 1891 1 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Wheatcroft, Nelson To Rita Lawrence New York, 25 January 1893 1 page a.n.s. (Box 1)
  - Wheatcroft, Nelson To Alice M. Lawrence New York, 25 April 1893 2 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Williard, Paul To Alice M. Lawrence New York, 20 April 1893 1 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Yrmonde, Eugene To Alice M. Lawrence New York, 1892 1 page a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Yrmonde, Eugene Receipt for Salary New York, 9 April 1892 1 page ms.d.s. (Box 1)
  - Unidentified Correspondence [n.p.], 10-11 May 1892 5 items 1 Folder (Box 1)
- Series II: Amateur Theater
  - Note: The series contains material related to the Lawrence sisters' work with theater, other personalities in theater, and charitable efforts. (Box 1)
  - Invoices, property lists New York, 1892-1893 (Box 1)
  - Programs, flyers, awards New York, 1887-1892 Note: Including list of photographs transferred from the Alice and Rita Lawrence Scrapbooks to the Dramatic Museum Portrait File (Box 1)
  - Clippings New York, 1889-1896 (Box 1)
  - Clippings on Sir Squire and Lady Bancroft New York, [n.d.] & 1926 (Box 1)
  - My Turn Next and The Serenade [n.p.], 15 October 1892 1 poster (Box 28)
  - Ladies Society Presented to Misses Lawrence for the December 4 1888 production of Blue and Cherry [n.p.], 1888 1 satin banner Note: For the relief of sufferers of yellow fever (Box 28)
- Series III: Scrapbooks
  - Note: The series contains five scrapbooks from the Lawrences' acting careers. The scrapbooks contain programs, souvenirs, and clippings. (Box 28)
  - Rita Lawrence Book 1 [n.p.], 1882-1891 (Box 28)
  - Alice Lawrence Book 1 [n.p.], 1874-1889 (Box 28)
  - Rita Lawrence Book 2 [n.p.], 1890-1893 (Box 282)
  - Alice Lawrence Book 2 [n.p.], 1890-1892 (Box 282)
  - Alice Lawrence Book 3 [n.p.], 1893-1895 (Box 282)
- List or photographs transferred from the Alice and Rita Lawrence Scrapbooks to the Dramatic Museum Ephemera: Portrait File.
  - Allen, Edward Heron (2)
  - Amory, Mathilde see: Madison, Mathilde
  - Barnard, Nanette (Mrs Horace) see: Widdleton, Nanette
  - Barry, Helen
  - Bedlow, Henry
  - Belasco, David (2)
  - Bond, Frederick (2)
  - Boynton, C. E.
  - Brady, Katheryn M.
  - Burroughs, William (2 )
  - Cary, John D.
  - Cayvan, Georgia with: Kelcey, Herbert
  - Collins, Laura Sedgwick
  - Coolidge, Palmer with: Lawrence, Alice Montgomery
  - Cutting, Robert Livingston, Jr. with: Lawrence, Alice Montgomery
  - Croly, Vida
  - Denison, Mathilde (Mrs. Charles) see Madison, Mathilde
  - Dyas, Ada and H. J. Montague
  - Gale, Minna K. (4)
  - Gale, Minna K. (5) with: Lawrence, Rita Woodhull
  - Griswold, Mrs Daniel Payne see: Robe, Annie
  - Grovesteen, Bessie(2} with: Lawrence, Rita Woodhull
  - Harris, Katharine (Mrs Sidney) see: Brady, Katheryn M.
  - Haynes, Minna see: Gale, Minna K.
  - Heaton, Gilbert
  - Henderson, Grace
  - Hendrickson, Mrs George Lincoln See: Vaux, Marion
  - Hill, Caroline (2)
  - Hopper, Will
  - Ireland, Joseph N.
  - Jackson, Ann
  - Kelcey, Herbert (3)
  - Kelcey, Herbert & Georgia Cayvan
  - Kelcey, Caroline Hill (Mrs Herbert) see: Hill, Caroline
  - Kershaw, Edmund (2)
  - Lamb, Herbert see: Kelcey, Herbert
  - Lawrence, Alice Montgomery (4)
  - Lawrence, Alice Montgomery & Rita Woodhull
  - Lawrence (3)
  - Lawrence, Alice M., Rita W.
  - Lawrence, & Sophie Clinch Tilley
  - Lawrence (Mrs W.T.) (5)
  - Lawrence, Alice M., Rita W.
  - Lawrence, Minna K. Gale, Henry Miller, &George W.
  - Nicholas (2) Lawrence, Alice M., Rita W. Lawrence, &Robert Lee Morrell (2)
  - Lawrence, Alice M., Rita W.
  - Lawrence, & Henry Miller
  - Lawrence, Alice M., Rita W.
  - Lawrence, Horace Porter, & Mr. Proctor (2)
  - Lawrence, Alice M., Rita W.
  - Lawrence, Palmer Coolidge, Robert Livingston Cutting, Jr., & Robert Lee Morrell (2)
  - Lawrence, Rita Woodhull (8)
  - Lawrence, Rita W. & Henry Miller
  - Lawrence, Rita W. Minna K. Gale, & three others
  - Lawrence, Rita W. Minna K. Gale, Bessie Grovestein, & Charles C. Ransom (2)
  - Lawrence, Sophie Clinch Tilley (Mrs William Thomas) with:Lawrence, Alice M. Leslie, Elsie (2)
  - Madison, Mathilde (2)
  - Merrill, W. A.
  - Miller, Henry with; Lawrence, Alice M.
  - Miller, Henry with: Lawrence, Rita W.
  - Montague, Harry J.
  - Montague, Harry J. with: Dyas, Ada
  - Morrell, Robert Lee with: Lawrence, Alice M.
  - Nicholas, George W.
  - Nicholas, George W. with: Lawrence, Alice M.
  - Pauling, Gracie
  - Porter, Horace with: Lawrence, Alice M..
  - Potter, Cora Urquhart (Mrs James Brown) (2)
  - Potter, Cora Urquhart (Mrs James Brown) & Alice M. Lawrence
  - Potter, Cora Urquhart (Mrs James Brown) & her daughter Anne Urquhart Potter Stillman
  - (Mrs James A.)
  - Proctor, Mr with: Lawrence, Alice M.
  - Ramsay, Walden
  - Ransom, Charles C. with: Lawrence, Rita W.
  - Robe, Annie (Mrs Daniel Payne Griswold) (2)
  - Stanhope, Adeline
  - Stillman, Anne Urquhart Potter (Mrs James A.) with: Potter, Cora Urquhart
  - Stoddard, Lorimer
  - Thorpe, Courtenay (2)
  - Throop, George Enos
  - Tilley, Mary Madison see: Lawrence, Rita W.
  - Vaux, Marion (3)
  - West, Percita
  - Wheatcroft, Adeline Stanhope (Mrs Nelsonl see: Stanhope, Adeline)
  - Wheatcroft, Nelson (5)
  - Whitten, Mrs Thomas
  - Widdleton, Nanette
  - Williams, Sally
  - Winter, Elsie Leslie (Mrs Jefferson) see: Leslie, Elsie
  - Wood, William T.